and these are two basically different
groups to about an example with a
certain degree of overlap and I wanted
especially to pay tribute to a number of
people like brandy Keeler and number of
others that I Peter president who shared
both of those obsessions and I wanted to
include and I said who who are committed
as I went to the movement against
nuclear war and in smallville internment
in our case the Vietnam many many and it
occurred to me that somebody that I
always understood sharing those two
concerns and commitments and obsessions
was my friend cyber if the cold was but
I knew that I would not like to be
described as committed to a movement
he's a piece of authorities for
investigative journalism and even if I
made a distinction there I had a feeling
that he would he would be uneasy with
but the truth is this is a man who is
passionately committed to the best
aspects of our Constitution there are
some better than others
the article one section eight the fact
it should be a congress that decides
when we get into a war and when they do
that that should be in accord with the
UN Charter and against aggression
somebody who understands the dangers of
nuclear war totally passionate about it
in private and what comes out of that is
truth in the firm's of realistic
realistic report about when the
government is deceiving us and when it's
policies are based online ignoring our
Constitution so he like Chelsea Manning
is a hero of mine I'm very happy that
this object sounds or has been given
toward to both of us share of civil
thank you
[Applause]
very much wanted to pay tribute to cider
for very specifically assets in April
2006 he revealed from massive lager news
that the torch every Bush administration
in particular Vice President Richard
Cheney Hayward plans for tax lights
print excellent Iran and specifically
for prepare nuclear attacks on a run and
then the crew chiefs were opposed to
this and criticized it of course they
can only go so far under certain
authority works he revealed that as
philip ii of the former CIA official
both reveal this planning and it is my
belief based on following that very
closely it's been a very important
aspect of my life ever since in the
eleven years since to avert any such
attack i believe that it was cypress and
filter always reporting at that time
that blame George tell me which to
reject the strong urging of Richard
Cheney to use nuclear weapons against
Iran to the cosmati for the world and I
believe that he's never gotten the
credit that he deserves for that I mean
I I think we all were very very to thank
you for giving me the opportunity
[Applause]
[Music]
well thank you daniel ellsberg both for
the depth of perspective and for the
current warnings very timely and very
frightening I would say so thank you
very much for participating in this and
I wished I could have been here with us
tonight but other constraints applied he
received his award slightly earlier in
the evening but was very honored to be
another Sam Adams laureate so thank you
so the next phase of this evening I'd
like to call on to stage three on three
next speakers first of all John Kiriakou
please
[Applause]
[Music]
right please could join us as well
[Applause]
[Music]
and thirdly ray mcgovern
where is he sitting
[Applause]
[Music]
okay I will come and join you at the
table as well so and I think first up we
have Android I don't know ray will
probably have a better idea on that one
perhaps we should address questions at
the end of the evening because we have
microphones set up so let's stick with
the agenda for now yes so Ann can I
introduce you you're going to be
speaking for five minutes on integrity
and intelligence you serve 29 years in
the US Army and retired as a colonel
she was a US diplomat and resigned in
March 2003 in opposition to push his war
in Iraq and she's a passionate peace
activist
[Applause]
first I want to address madea's question
because if we don't address it she's
going to keep asking you Chelsea Manning
is not here as my understanding is
because there are other things that were
coming up she had hoped to be here but
she isn't here and that's about all I
know ciphers made a decision that he
wanted to have the the same animus award
our Lord had had a private dinner and he
thanks us very much for that and wishes
us all well though here at the the
conference on war and the environment so
with that I want to say thank you all so
much for being here it's so important
that we're here to talk about this
intersection between war and the
environment and as we are all here
talking about an aspect of our
government our government and its
intelligence agencies I myself served
both in the in the army and in the State
Department
I never was officially an intelligence
officer however as a as a US diplomat
even though I was not CIA
everybody's an intelligence officer
everybody that was working in the
government and working overseas is
actually don't listening talking to
people and one hopes they're talking to
them in a positive beneficial way for
the whole world we know sometimes that's
not true
but one thing I would like to emphasize
is that right now in this terrifically
difficult time that we have with the
Trump administration which is gutting
our government and many people may agree
with Trump that maybe it's over maybe we
got too many people in the government
how many of you all think we have too
many people in government
yeah well and which which ones should go
okay yeah we got 1.4 million people in
the military okay how many of you all
think we ought to reduce that the CIA
how many would like to have the EPA stay
the Department of Education to stay okay
how many would like to have what else do
we have Department of Energy
[Applause]
there we go I like this crowd okay so
what I want to talk about though is a
little bit of the organization that I
spent the last sixteen years that I was
in the government with and that was the
State Department and the State
Department as you all know the reduction
under the Trump administration is to be
twenty nine percent twenty nine percent
of the budget of the State Department is
being taken away
one could argue okay we do have a lot of
programs a lot of programs that we have
that for our ability to work in other
cultures and some people say well that's
all that's intelligence we are gathering
intelligence about other places well I
think that kind of intelligence is
worthy I think we need to know a lot
about other cultures know you we needed
to know about them we need to know
enough about them to know that we
shouldn't be killing them that we should
be we should be friends with people we
should know enough about them to
appreciate all of the culture that they
bring to us and every one of those
cultures that we're going after right
now have a much longer history by how
many thousands of years that our pitiful
little 240 to 240 years I mean we are
such babes in the woods on this thing
and yet we're going after huge long I
mean Iraq Iran had thousands and
thousands of years old that they are we
look at Korea Korea that was only
divided 70 years ago after World War two
we divided it we and the Russians
divided that and now we vilified part of
that peninsula the northern part of that
peninsula beyond belief
we vilified the North Koreans until most
Americans not you all I don't think but
most Americans think that North Koreans
are just horrible terrible people and
yes their government has done some very
brutal things and yes our government
done some very brutal things you know on
the issues of North Korea of Iran the
issue of Syria and of Iraq the issue of
Somalia and of Libya our ability to use
our government in the in a beneficial
way that we as Americans are able to
travel to countries and travel to
countries proudly about our own country
but that's not the way it is now is it
no we don't allow seven countries now to
get visas to come to the United States
and there is now being retaliation
against us that we it's more difficult
for Americans to travel these types of
things are parts of the huge problems
that we face now with the Trump
administration and while I know this
little comment that I've made has not
really been quite the intelligence thing
that maybe you're looking for but I
think that's just like what I'd like to
say that we need to hold our government
accountable and we need to to go after
it when we know it's doing wrong and I
know you all do it I know that you'll be
out at the White House anytime you can
let me just mention that for the next
three weeks we're going to have a noon
vigil we're going to follow the Catholic
workers on there every Friday but we're
going to have an
Vigil every day on the issues of North
Korea and in Iran so that our voices
will be right there right at Trump
speaking right to him it's our country
and we have to make sure it's the
country that we admire and respect thank
you
[Music]
[Applause]
Thank You Anne fort is always an amazing
rallying call get out there and do stuff
I would like to introduce John Kiriakou
again and person who probably needs very
little introduction that is an event
like this and I had the pleasure of
sharing a panel with him in Berlin a few
months ago and just to hear the stories
of what it was like for him when he was
imprisoned for exposing the crimes of
others just blew me away it's every time
as bad as I thought it was gonna be I
began working for the CIA on the Monday
after the Friday that Ray McGovern
retired in January of 1990 so we never
actually crossed paths inside the CIA
but that week that first week was very
important I was so proud to have been
hired by the CIA and indeed that very
first day along with a couple of hundred
other new hires I put my right hand in
the air and I swore an oath to protect
the Constitution of the United States
against all enemies foreign and domestic
in retrospect I now realized I was
probably the only one in the room who
actually took that seriously one of the
things that the director of security
told us that week that was an
introductory week for all of us was
never to do anything that you wouldn't
be proud to see on the front page of the
Washington Post
I also took that seriously and so in
2002 when a senior officer in the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center asked me if I
wanted to be trained in torture I said
no I said it's torture no it's not it's
enhanced interrogation techniques I said
that's a torture program I speak
frequently at colleges and universities
around the country and I like to ask
students their real-life questions now
as background there is no ethics
training at the CIA nothing nothing
the problem with that besides the
obvious is what a CIA psychiatrist once
told me he said that the CIA actively
seeks to hire people who have
sociopathic tendencies not sociopaths
but people with sociopathic tendencies
sociopaths have no conscience and with
no conscience you can easily pass a
polygraph exam because you don't react
to anything but sociopaths are
impossible to control people who have
sociopathic tendencies do have a
conscience but they're willing to
operate in moral legal and ethical gray
areas the problem is there's no real way
to weed out the sociopaths and if you
can't weed out the sociopaths
you can't weed out the Psychopaths and
the Psychopaths because they're
psychopaths rise to the leadership
positions
so let's say that you are a CIA case
officer and you're working overseas and
it can be anywhere
well let's say the Middle East you're in
Egypt you're in a hotel room and you
have recruited a member of a a bonafide
terrorist group al Qaeda Hezbollah Isis
whatever it is and this guy has been
fantastic everything that he's told you
has been true and you've used his
information to actually disrupt future
terrorist attacks
so he's been vetted and he's really
great so you're in this hotel room and
you're meeting with him and at the start
of the meeting he says listen before we
meet I want to tell you I've given you
everything I've told you everything
that's been true you saved American
lives now you're gonna do something for
me you're gonna go out and you're gonna
get me a prostitute right now or I'm
never cooperating with you again so I
want to see a show of hands how many
people would get him the prostitute some
not many the answer is sure I mean you
know it's he's a scumbag of course but
your job is to deal with scumbags and
you would you would be expected to go
out and get him the prostitute what if
he asks for a child prostitute
absolutely not under any circumstances
but that's not the CIA talking that's
John Kerry Anka talking because there's
no rule your job as a CIA case officer
is to break the laws of the country that
you're serving in that's your job your
job is to commit espionage which in most
countries is a death penalty crime your
job is to convince people to commit
treason for you because they like you so
much or they like the money that you're
giving them so much so because it's the
nature of your job to break the law
there are no rules that are written for
you to carry out that job now the
problem there is that most CIA case
officers would procure the child child
prostitute
and even if they felt funny about it
they would be told by headquarters you
have a job to do this is a bonafide
source here go do your job
that's the problem or the nature of the
problem of ethics and intelligence
operations there are no ethics and
intelligence operations I've come to the
conclusion after all these years that
there probably doesn't need to be a CIA
[Applause]
was right in 1976 when he said that the
CIA should be broken up John Kennedy was
right in 1963 when he said the CIA
should be broken up
certainly other governmental
organizations can carry out those duties
and to tell you the truth I'm hard
pressed to point to any CIA successes
over the last half a century other than
meddling in elections we always seem to
do that short term successfully long
term unsuccessfully
but like I said the bottom line is there
are no ethics and intelligence
operations you either enter the CIA with
your own set of moral values or you
don't and again if you don't you're
probably gonna do pretty well there
sorry I had to keep this very short
thank you very much for your time
[Applause]
[Music]
junk thank you so much for like those
comments and it reminds me of the old
issue in the UK with the with mi6 which
is the UK's CIA equivalent and one of
the recruitment questions was do you
have ethical flexibility terribly
British way of saying are you a
sociopath
[Laughter]
on that note we're going to talk to a
former CI ray mcgovern co-creators
veteran intelligence professionals for
sanity VIPs to expose how intelligence
was being falsified to justify war
justify war in Iraq formerly a CIA
analyst of 27 years he prepared this
president's Daily Brief and chaired the
National Intelligence Estimates and also
someone who really got the ball rolling
with Sam Adams and the award every year
so thank you Ray and ten minutes ten
minutes
this is working this is working I guess
good what a treat it is to see guys out
there that's just incredible let me just
say a couple of words I was a very close
friend of Sam Adams he and I served
together matter of fact we entered the
agency together on the same day about
seven months before John Kennedy was
killed Sam was a straight arrow and the
only other person I think in this room
that knew him was I Hersh
is there anybody else here from the old
set that knew Sam Adams okay well let me
just say that when we established the
Sam Adams Award for integrity
intelligence we couldn't do otherwise
because Coleen Rowley had just blown the
whistle on all the terrible things the
mistakes and worse the FBI had done
before what I love him
matter of fact if they hadn't done those
things it would have been a cinch to
stop 9/11 and then we had NSA people
come out of the woodwork who said there
was evidence in NSA's database that
showed exactly what was going to happen
before 9/11 but that database was only
that only costs the 30 million dollars
they discarded that went with one that
cost three billion dollars with a B as
in boy and that wasn't working and so we
never got that information so these the
consequential things now today the 22nd
of September is exactly 50 years and one
month since general Abrams who was
general Westmoreland's deputy in Saigon
sent in a cable from Saigon disputing
the numbers that Sam Adams had come up
with which the numbers were between 500
and 600 thousand troops that is formed
communist
in South Vietnam general Westmoreland
said no no it can't be more than two
hundred and ninety-nine thousand two
hundred and ninety-nine thousand a
little fishy to you that was the the
ceiling you couldn't go higher than that
Abrams said in a very sensitive cable on
the 22nd of August so fifty years and
one month ago and it said this quote we
can't possibly go with the higher
numbers because we have been projecting
an image of success in this war and
there's nothing that we could do despite
all the caveats that we could adduce to
avoid the press from drawing an
erroneous and gloomy conclusion 1967
just a couple months before Tet just a
couple of months before all hell broke
loose Sam to his dying day regretted
that it didn't go down to the New York
Times bureau in in Washington and so do
I regret that you see you have that
means I see the puzzled faces here you
have to know that in those days the New
York Times was an independent newspaper
and actually if you gave them some
documentary evidence they would put it
on the front page it was really quite
remarkable
most young people don't know that so
let me go through here very quickly what
happened since then well you know Dan
Ellsberg who spoke beautifully here
before is also a good friend of mine
and he and I on the third Sam Adams
Award first we had Koli and rally then
we had Catherine Gunn who worked for the
British intelligence and who blew the
whistle on what NSA was asking GCHQ to
do I won't go into all that but she was
an incredibly courageous person now Dan
Ellsberg and I and others got together
the following year and we formed the
truth-telling coalition okay now we had
the lawyers we had everything wrong you
and you we would disconsolate that there
was nobody throwing the whistle we had
to wait six years then we had Bradley
Bradley Manning and Chelsea Manning yeah
we had hates Snowden then we had this
Tom Drake again all the people from NSA
who spoke truth to power and suffered
mightily for it and stoughton of course
was edified by Tom and by Bill Binney
because bill Binney spoke out even
before Snowden did and when we gave
Snowden when we gave bill bunny the
award two years ago Snowden said you
know you got it wrong on that citation
you said that bill got the idea from me
it wasn't that way without bill Binney
there would be no it Snowden okay and
when it got to Hong Kong he said I knew
I had to do this this way to a achieve
my mission get them to cut the material
out and number two to have some
reasonable prospect that I could you
know live live for a few more months
okay
so Tom Drake showed him that way because
tom was persecuted for four years with
our judicial system who actually forged
so classified unclassified documents
that they said they found in this thing
the judge was so angry and Tom had a
public defender by that he was out of
money the joke was so he say you Justice
Department lawyers get that get out of
my court and let me show your face to me
again
forging evidence to convict this guy so
what I'm saying here is that the
whistleblowers that Dan Ellsberg I and
Koli around the others were lusting
after and never felt that did show up in
2004 did show up and that they're
showing up big time let's do it yeah a
Tom there's Tom Drake still here yeah
he's right there
Tom Harriet
[Applause]
[Music]
another one of our parties is jesselyn
Radack
who was a butcher whistleblower for the
department
you know for a long time and Sam Adams
associates all we have were women
winners I mean if it weren't for Craig
Murray the British ambassador to his
Becky stun they come on the scene there
he was the fourth one but just a little
radio what she did was she told the
Department of Justice hey um I'm the
ethics person here and when you when you
interrogate John Walker Lindh he's an
American citizen I'm sure you're gonna
read him his rights correct
Edie correct she was not only
disregarded but dissed and you have ran
into about the same level of programs
that Tom Drake did so they're both the
real deal and there are others here from
from other years that have have won what
I want to talk about is this in the last
two minutes
it's another whistleblower nobody knows
about it is already given Julian Assange
heaps and heaps of documents matter of
fact when Julia saj announced in early
March of this year that this one
contractor for the CIA had given him
information that was more comprehensive
and more important that all the stuff
that Ed Snowden had released Oh anybody
hear about that no oh okay
did you hear from the New York Times
well long story short this is a treasure
trove it's called vault 7 now I'll just
mention one thing that didn't make the
New York Times and that is it it
includes something called marble marble
framework now this is a cyber offensive
tool that allows the CIA to hack into a
network or server or a computer and the
word is up on the scape $0.35 word in
CIA
aquascape who hacked in and then leave
little traces in foreign languages like
oh they worked in five Chinese Arabic
Farsi Korean and oh yeah Russian now
think about that guys see if you can
connect some dots here you know because
nobody else is connecting those dots so
if I used to say that you know psy and
the professionalism with which he works
and how deeply dependent he is on people
within the structure that's incredible
and he does incredible work but so does
Julian Assange okay and what I have
[Applause]
that's not just because he's one of our
Sam Adams associates winners in 2010 but
because he is the one that this
contractor NCAA knew they could go to
who is it nobody knows anybody been
arrested no does he still work with
contract see you don't know so what I'm
saying here is that we have a really
good thing going it's only what 2000
Ford what 2,000 what cities there were
13 subtract 13 years after the Dan
Ellsberg and I would disconsolate about
how there were no truth tells us there
were no no whistleblowers it's big time
now to the degree you can support them
and degree you can spread the
information that they give they may not
be in the New York Times okay
but spread it with your friends make
sure people know and if you live next
door to a CIA person mow is lon
I do do something nice to them and get a
kind of rep or recruit them and have
Thanks
[Applause]
thank you very much for you for that
highly subversive speech we have two
final speakers for this evening
Todd Pierce a law war expert I also have
trouble saying that retired jag lawyers
his views are unrepresented with his
former employers which is probably just
as well from what I gather he's going to
say so Todd would you like to come on
the stage and kollene as well retired
FBI agent and if you would like to take
the podium together
[Applause]
[Music]
so if you can't recruit your neighbor
the CIA operative I have another
suggestion the first amendment right now
and it ties in with this real this topic
of intelligent egg rity and intelligence
in a time of war Todd has researched
everything from the Civil War I mean he
knows this what they call the law of war
unfortunately the law of war is hardly
any law it means that you get rid of
your Bill of Rights and especially the
First Amendment if you remember back to
our great Abraham Lincoln one of the
first things he did was round up the
editors a couple hundred editors were
imprisoned for criticizing the war and
you know Todd will talk a little more
about this but the truth is they it goes
back to Vietnam syndrome if anybody's
watching if anybody's watching the burns
Nova documentary right now you will know
that this this big effort to mislead the
public so that you can keep public
opinion pushing for more war in order to
win it and this was a huge thing not
only during Vietnam but afterwards you
had all kinds of suppression of a First
Amendment even to the point of shooting
people in protests etc right now the
current